<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the last great fight at sea, July 29. and 31. between the English and the Dutch, as it was presented to the Councill of State in two letters sent them from General Monck: as also an estimate of the enemies ships taken, fired, and sunk, with the number of prisoners; together with what loss we sustained on our side. Saturday August 6. At the Council of State at White-Hall, ordered, that these letters and estimate be forthwith printed and published. John Thurloe Secr.</title>
            <author>Albemarle, George Monck, Duke of, 1608-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E710_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203920</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863696</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 109:E710[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the last great fight at sea, July 29. and 31. between the English and the Dutch, as it was presented to the Councill of State in two letters sent them from General Monck: as also an estimate of the enemies ships taken, fired, and sunk, with the number of prisoners; together with what loss we sustained on our side. Saturday August 6. At the Council of State at White-Hall, ordered, that these letters and estimate be forthwith printed and published. John Thurloe Secr.</title>
                  <author>Albemarle, George Monck, Duke of, 1608-1670.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, Henry Hills, and Thomas Brewster, printers to the Council of State,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIII. [1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 8:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naval battles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE RELATION OF THE LAST Great Fight at Sea, July 29. and 31. between the ENGLISH and the DUTCH, As it was preſented to the Councill of State in two Letters ſent them from <hi>GENERAL MONCK:</hi> AS ALSO An Eſtimate of the Enemies Ships taken, fired, and ſunk, with the Number of Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; together with what loſs we ſuſtained on our ſide.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>SATURDAY AUGUST 6.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At the Council of State at White-Hall, Ordered, That theſe Letters and Estimate be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Thurloe Secr.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert, Henry Hills,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> Printers to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State, MDCLIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:166654:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166654:2"/>
            <head>For the Right Honourable the Council of State at White-Hall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I was diſpatching the other Letter comming herewith, the ſame mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Scout a-head diſcovered a Fleet, which in a ſhort time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet come from the <hi>Wellings,</hi> conſiſting of 97 ſail, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, whereof 90 men of War; we made what ſail after them we could, which the enemy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, ſtood away from us, ſo that it was five a clock in the evening before any of our Frigots could engage them, and neer ſeven a clock before this Ship came up with them, the greateſt part of our Fleet being a ſtern, ſo that not above thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our ſhips and frigots came to engage; yet we continued fighting until 9 at night, at which time being dark, we were forced to forbear. The enemy this night got the weather gage of us, by ſtanding to the Northward, when we ſuppoſed they had ſtood to the Southward, as we did; and yeſterday being much wind, and durty wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nothing was done, both Fleets finding it hard work to get off from a Lee ſhore, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166654:3"/>was the worſt to us, being in an enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; but this morning, being fair weather, and little wind, both Fleets prepared for a ſecond Engagement. To this time the Lord ſeemed to encourage the enemy, by laying the ſcales in the ballance, ſo that neither could tell which had the better, but good was the Lord unto us, who knew when to appear for his own people, though unworthy of ſo great a mercy; for this day after their great ſhips from the <hi>Texel</hi> were joined with them, being twenty five in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the Engagement began very hot from ſeven in the morning, and continued till one in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, the enemy having the weather-gage of us all the while; yet may we truly ſay, great was the Lord, and marvellous worthy to be praiſed, by his appearance on our behalf; for by this time the Lord ſo daunted their ſpirits, they now began to ſtand away from us, with all the ſails they could, there being ſunk, fired and taken of them, about thirty or fourty ſail, ſo far as we can diſcern, and are now in purſute of them, ſome of our Frigots being neer up with ſome of the ſternmoſt, &amp; am in good hopes that the ſame mighty preſence of the Lord will ſtill follow us, to the diſabling, taking or diſtroying of ſome more yet. There were nine flagge ſhips amongſt them, when we firſt engaged this morning, and they have but one left now ſo far as we can ſee. At preſent I am not in a capacity of giving your Lordſhips a more particular account, our hands and hearts being wholy taken up with the end of the work, and if the Lord will, you may expect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166654:3"/>(about two dayes hence) to have a further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof. Two of our ſhips were fired, (as ſuppoſed, by the enemy) ſome others diſabled by the loſs of their maſts, of which I have given the Commiſſioners a further account, for a preſent and ſpeedy ſupply, which I ſhall not trouble you with; but ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Reſolution off of</hi> Camperdown, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 31 July 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant, GEORGE MONCK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:166654:4"/>
            <head>For the Right Honourable the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE mine to you yeſterday (wherein I gave you an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the goodneſs of God towards us, and appearance for us in the Engagement with our enemies the day before, and that we were then in purſute of them) there hath little more been done, night drawing on, and the Dutch making directly for the Texell with what ſail they could, ſo that it was not thought fit to be ſo bold with the ſhore as they might, not knowing how the wind might take us, many of our Ships being much diſabled; but gave order to a ſmall veſſell or two to keep ſight of them till the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and obſerve what courſe they ſteer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who returning gave an account that the enemy ſteered the ſame night into the Texel harbour, and had boats with lights to ſhew them the way in, whereupon ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166654:4"/>at a Councill of War it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the whole Fleet ſhould forthwith ſet ſail for Southold Bay there to diſpoſe of ſuch Ships as are diſabled, alſo to ſend away our wounded men and priſoners, of which a certain account cannot be given at preſent, but hope to do it very ſuddenly being now upon it; but I do preſent your Lordſhips here encloſed with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Account, referring the condition of the Wives and Families of thoſe who are ſlain, to your Lordſhips tender care, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I doubt not but you will have reſpect to their neceſſities. I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Reſolution</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 2. 1653.</date> 18. <hi>Leagues to the Weſtward of the Texell.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant, <hi>GEORGE MONCK.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_prisoners">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166654:5"/>
            <head>An Eſtimate of Priſoners taken, alſo how many Ships of the Enemies ſunk and fired, and how many men of our own wounded and killed in the Engagement with the <hi>Dutch, Iuly 29,</hi> &amp; <hi>31. 1653.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Priſoners taken 1000</item>
               <item>Ships of the Enemies ſunk and fired, of which ſome were taken and afterwards fired, 30 or thereabouts.</item>
               <item>Men of our own ſlain 250</item>
               <item>Wounded 700</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Oak and one fire-ſhip of our own burnt.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
